Guide to the John C. Wilson Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
John C. Wilson Papers
1898-1978
YCAL MSS 1127
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
22.6
(74 boxes)
The John C. Wilson papers consist of scrapbooks, photographs, and other material documenting the life and work of American producer and director John C. Wilson.
Wilson, John C., approximately 1899-1961
Provenance
Acquired by gift and purchase, 2015-2016. For more information consult the appropriate curator.
Information About Access
This collection is open for research.
Box 60-61 (scrapbooks): Restricted fragile material. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
John C. Wilson (1899-1961)
Born in Trenton, New Jersey and educated at Phillips Academy and Yale University, John C. Wilson (1899-1961) worked briefly for C. D. Barney & Co. on Wall Street before becoming a producer and director. From the early 1930s to mid 1950s, Wilson served as Noel Coward's personal manager and, in 1934, with Coward, Lynn Fontanne, and Alfred Lunt, he established Transatlantic Productions, with exclusive production rights to Coward's plays in the United States. Wilson also served as co-director of the Westport Country Playhouse from the early 1940s to mid 1950s.
Description of the Papers
In Series I, sixty-one scrapbooks containing clippings, printed ephemera, and photographs document Wilson's life, activities, and interests. Clippings relate to Wilson's stage productions, stage and film actors, theater, and other topics. Photographic materials in Series II include photograph albums, studio and artists' portraits of Wilson, snapshots of Wilson and others, and publicity photographs of stage productions. There are photographs of Wilson, family members, friends, and stage colleagues, including: Wilson's wife, Natalie Paley, Leonora Corbett, Noel Coward, Martin Manulis, Armina Marshall, Mildred Natwick, Graham Payn, and Clifton Webb, among others. Other papers include correspondence, printed material, such as playbills, writings, and other material.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: Series I. Scrapbooks, 1919-1961. II. Photographs, 1900-1969. III. Other Papers, 1898-1978.
Related Materials
Additional material by or relating to Wilson can be found in the John C. Wilson Theater Collection on Noel Coward (GEN MSS 608).
Actors -- United States; Dramatists; Theater -- Production and direction -- New York (State) -- New York; Theater -- United States; Theatrical producers and directors -- United States; Clippings (information artifacts); Photographic prints; Playbills; Scrapbooks; Actors -- United States; Dramatists -- United States; Theatrical producers and directors -- United States; Corbett, Leonora, 1908-1960; Coward, Noel, 1899-1973; Fontanne, Lynn, 1887-1983; Lunt, Alfred, 1892-1977; Manulis, Martin, 1915-2007; Marshall, Armina; Natwick, Mildred, 1905-1994; Paley, Natalie; Payn, Graham; Webb, Clifton, 1893-1966; Wilson, John C., approximately 1899-1961; Transatlantic Productions; Westport Country Playhouse (Organization: Westport, Conn.)
- Scrapbooks, 1919-1961; Series I; 15; (61 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I. consists of 61 scrapbooks containing material relating to Wilson's life, activities, and interests. Scrapbooks contain clippings chiefly, dating from 1919 through 1961, but printed ephemera and photographs can also be found. Clippings relate to Wilson's stage productions, stage and film actors, and other topics.
  Clippings chiefly in English, with some material in French.
  - Untitled, 1919-1922, undated (Box 60)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Box 60: Restricted fragile material. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Untitled, 1930-1936, undated (Box 1)
  - Untitled, 1933, undated (Box 2)
  - "J.C.W. 1934 Vol. I." (Box 3)
  - "J.C.W. 1934 Vol. II.", 1934, undated (Box 4)
  - "J.C.W. 1935 Vol. I.", 1935, undated (Box 5)
  - "J.C.W. 1936 Vol. I.", 1936, undated (Box 6)
  - "J.C.W. 1936 Vol. II., 1936, undated (Box 7)
  - "J.C.W. 1937 Vol. I.", 1937, undated (Box 8)
  - "J.C.W. 1937 Vol. II.", 1937, undated (Box 9)
  - "J.C.W. 1937 Special Coronation Volume", 1937, undated (Box 10)
  - "J.C.W. 1938 Vol. I.", 1938, undated (Box 11)
  - "J.C.W. 1938 Vol. II.", 1938, undated (Box 12)
  - "J.C.W. 1939 Vol. I.", 1939, undated (Box 13)
  - "J.C.W. 1939 Vol. II.", 1939, undated (Box 14)
  - "J.C.W. 1940 Vol. I.", 1940, undated (Box 15)
  - "J.C.W. 1940 Vol. II.", 1940, undated (Box 16)
  - "J.C.W. 1941 Vol. I.", 1941, undated (Box 17)
  - "J.C.W. 1941 Vol. II.", 1941, undated (Box 18)
  - "J.C.W. 1942 Vol. I.", 1942, undated (Box 19)
  - "J.C.W. 1942 Vol. II.", 1942, undated (Box 20)
  - "J.C.W. 1943 Vol. I.", 1943, undated (Box 21)
  - "J.C.W. 1943 Vol. II.", 1943, undated (Box 22)
  - "J.C.W. 1944 Vol. I.", 1944, undated (Box 23)
  - "J.C.W. 1944 Vol. II.", 1944, undated (Box 24)
  - "J.C.W. 1945 Vol. I.", 1945, undated (Box 25)
  - "J.C.W. 1945 Vol. II.", 1945, undated (Box 26)
  - "J.C.W. 1946 Vol. I.", 1946, undated (Box 27)
  - "J.C.W. 1946 Vol. II.", 1946, undated (Box 28)
  - "J.C.W. 1947 Vol. I.", 1947, undated (Box 29)
  - "J.C.W. 1947 Vol. II.", 1947, undated (Box 30)
  - "J.C.W. 1948 Vol. I.", 1948, undated (Box 31)
  - "J.C.W. 1948 Vol. II.", 1948, undated (Box 32)
  - "J.C.W. 1949 Vol. I.", 1949, undated (Box 33)
  - "J.C.W. 1949 Vol. II.", 1949, undated (Box 34)
  - "J.C.W. 1950 Vol. I.", 1950, undated (Box 35)
  - "J.C.W. 1950 Vol. II.", 1950, undated (Box 36)
  - "J.C.W. 1951 Vol. I.", 1951, undated (Box 37)
  - "J.C.W. 1951 Vol. II.", 1951, undated (Box 38)
  - "J.C.W. 1952 Vol. I.", 1952, undated (Box 39)
  - "J.C.W. 1952 Vol. II", 1952, undated (Box 40)
  - "J.C.W. 1953 Vol. I.", 1953, undated (Box 41)
  - "J.C.W. 1953 Vol. II.", 1953, undated (Box 42)
  - "J.C.W. 1954 Vol. I.", 1954, undated (Box 43)
  - "J.C.W. 1954 Vol. II.", 1954, undated (Box 44)
  - "J.C.W. 1955 Vol. I.", 1955, undated (Box 45)
  - "J.C.W. 1955 Vol. II.", 1955, undated (Box 46)
  - "J.C.W. 1956 Vol. I.", 1956, undated (Box 47)
  - "J.C.W. 1956 Vol. II.", 1956, undated (Box 48)
  - "J.C.W. 1956 Vol. III.", 1956, undated (Box 49)
  - "J.C.W. 1957 Vol. I.", 1957, undated (Box 50)
  - "J.C.W. 1957 Vol. II.", 1957, undated (Box 51)
  - "J.C.W. 1958 Vol. I.", 1958, undated (Box 52)
  - "J.C.W. 1958 Vol. II.", 1958, undated (Box 53)
  - "J.C.W. 1959 Vol. I.", 1959, undated (Box 54)
  - "J.C.W. 1959 Vol. II.", 1959, undated (Box 55)
  - "J.C.W. 1960 Vol. I.", 1960, undated (Box 56)
  - "J.C.W. 1960 Vol. II.", 1960, undated (Box 57)
  - "J.C.W. 1961 [Vol. I.]", 1961, undated (Box 58)
  - "J.C.W. 1961 Vol. II.", 1961, undated (Box 59)
  - "J.C.W.", circa 1936-1952, undated (Box 61)
    Box 61: Restricted fragile material. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
- Photographs, 1900-1969; Series II; 3.93; (4 boxes)
  Organized into three subseries: Photograph Albums, Studio and Artists' Portraits, and Other Photographs.
  Series II. Photographs contains photogaph albums, studio and artists' portraits of Wilson, snapshots of Wilson and others, and approximately 50 publicity photographs of stage productions of Wilson's "Broadway Shows." Albums document Wilson's childhood and trips to Europe in the 1920s and 1930s. Snapshots include Wilson's family, friends, and stage colleagues: Wilson's wife, Natalie Paley, Leonora Corbett, Noel Coward, Martin Manulis, Armina Marshall, Mildred Natwick, Graham Payn, and Clifton Webb, among others. The publicity photographs identify actors and productions.
  - Photograph Albums
    - Photograph album, [1925] (Box 62)
    - Photograph album, [1920s-1930s] (Box 63)
    - Photographs album ("JCW Childhood Photos"), circa 1905-[1950s] (Box 64)
    - Photograph album, 1939-1954, undated (Box 64)
    - Photograph album, undated (Box 64)
  - Studio and Artists' Portraits
    - Photographs of John C. Wilson by Cris Alexander, undated (Box 65)
    - Photographs of John C. Wilson by Cecil Beaton, 1933 (Box 65)
    - Photograph of John C. Wilson by Cecil Beaton, [1933] (Box 74 (Oversize))
    - Photographs of John C. Wilson by Maurice Beck and Helen MacGregor, 1926 (Box 74 (Oversize))
    - Photographs of John C. Wilson by Marcus Blechman, undated (Box 65)
    - Photograph of John C. Wilson by Ira L. Hill, undated (Box 74 (Oversize))
    - Photographs of John C. Wilson by Horst P. Horst, 1937, undated (Box 65)
    - Photograph of John C. Wilson by George Platt Lynes, undated (Box 65)
    - Photograph of John C. Wilson by Irving Penn, 1947 (Box 74 (Oversize))
  - Other Photographs
    - Wilson, John C., circa 1900-1950s; 3 (Box 65)
    - Wilson, John C. (with others), circa 1910-1950s (Box 65)
    - Wilson, John C. (with others), 1947, undated (Box 74 (Oversize))
    - Others, 1969, undated (Box 65)
    - Others, undated (Box 74 (Oversize))
    - Publicity photographs, 1943, undated; 2 (Box 65)
- Other Papers, 1898-1978; Series III; 3.67; (8 boxes)
  Organized into four subseries: Correspondence, Printed Material, Writings, and Other Material.
  Series III. Other Papers includes correspondence, printed material, writings, and other material. Correspondents includes Noel Coward and Wilson's niece, Barbara (Cart) Macauley, and sister, Dorothy Wilson. The printed materials feature approximately 100 playbills for stage productions relating to Wilson and Coward. Writings include drafts of biographical and autobiographical works, "Actors Aren't People" and "Stagestruck" respectively. Other personal and juvenile items, such as a baby book, coloring book, and locks of Wilson's hair, can also be found.
  - Correspondence
    Organized into two subdivisions: John C. Wilson Correspondence and Third Party Correspondence.
    - John. C. Wilson Correspondence
      - Cannons of Hollywood, 1938 February 8 (Box 66)
      - Coward, Noel, 1951 February 20 (Box 66)
      - Macauley, Barbara (Cart), 1945-1955 (Box 66)
      - Wilson, Dorothy, 1918-1928 (Box 66)
    - Third Party Correspondence
      - Coward, Noel to Barbara (Cart) Macauley, 1933, 1970 (Box 66)
      - Coward, Noel to Barbara (Cart) Macauley, 1969 March 17 (Box 74 (Oversize))
      - Loos, Anita to Barbara (Cart) Macauley, 1951-1978, undated (Box 66)
      - Manulis, Martin to Barbara [(Cart) Macauley], undated (Box 66)
  - Printed Material
    Organized into three subdivisions: Periodicals, Playbills, and Other Ephemera.
    - Periodicals
      - The Theatre, 1902 (Box 67)
      - "Special editions", 1950 (Box 68)
    - Playbills
      - Playbills, 1928-1948; 5 (Box 69)
      - Playbills, 1948-1955, undated; 5 (Box 70)
      - Playbills, undated; 2 (Box 71)
    - Other ephemera
      - Calling cards, undated (Box 71)
      - Clipping, 1952 June 3 (Box 71)
      - School program, 1912 June 12 (Box 71)
  - Writings
    Arranged alphabetically by title.
    - "Actors Aren't People," draft, autograph manuscript and typescript, corrected, circa 1958; 3 (Box 71)
    - "Actors Aren't People," draft, typescript carbon, circa 1958; 2 (Box 71)
    - "Actors Aren't People," draft, typescript (photocopy) (4 copies), undated; 4 (Box 72)
    - "Stagestruck," draft, typescript carbon, undated (Box 72)
    - "Stagestruck," draft, typescript (photocopy) (4 copies), undated (Box 72)
    - "Copy of Speech by Anita Loose," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 73)
  - Other Material
    Arranged alphabetically by material type.
    - Address books, undated (Box 73)
    - Baby book, circa 1899-1912 (Box 73)
    - "Bloomer Girl" material, 1944 (Box 73)
    - Certificate, 1920 (Box 74 (Oversize))
    - Coloring book, circa 1898-1902 (Box 73)
    - Diploma, 1922 (Box 74 (Oversize))
    - Empty cloth bag, undated (Box 73)
    - Locks of hair, circa 1900-1901 (Box 73)
    - Name plate, undated (Box 73)
    - Petition, 1910 March (Box 74 (Oversize))
    - Untitled picture book, 1903 April (Box 73)